Guide to the Stanford University, Department of History, Honors Theses
Stanford University. Libraries.
- Theses, 2004-2005; Accession ARCH-2005-195
  - Koplowicz, Amy Lisa Isaacs, Secret Weapon of the Union?: The Sewing Machine and Civil War America., 2005 (Box 2)
  - Kosicki, Piotr H., From Christian Democracy to Secular Spirituality: Spiritual Ideologies and the Origins of the European Community's Political Culture, 1948-1953., 2005 (Box 2)
  - Montague-Breakwell, Chris, The Original Intent of the Alien Tort Claims Act., 2005 (Box 2)
  - Nuckols, Jennifer S., Garbage Room Perspective: How an uneducated black slum-dweller provided a window into understanding the politics, culture and psychology of Brazil in the latter half of the twentieth century., May 2005 (Box 2)
  - Nunez, Carlos Ismael, Accidental Fascists: Historical Circumstances Leading to a "Fascist" Movement in Mexico during the 1930's., May 2005 (Box 2)
  - Ortiz, Michael Rian, National Inquest: An Analytical Narrative of Senate Investigative Procedures 1954-1987., May 2005 (Box 2)
  - Rubens, Daniel Adams, Debating the Policy of Slavery in the Ohio Valley, 1787-1824., May 2005 (Box 2)
  - Shacham, Matan, "The Views of Vanoc": Arnold White as a Case Study of Modern English Antisemitism., May 11, 2005 (Box 2)
  - Stafford, Chase, Apartheid Atlantis: A Planned City in a Racist Society., May 11, 2005 (Box 3)
  - Stevens, Olivia, NGOs and the Rainbow Nation's Black Death: An Historical Analysis of the Capacity of the South African NGO Sector to Respond to HIV/AIDS., 2005 (Box 3)
  - Wilcox-Fogel, Megan, The Advantages and Disadvantages of History: The Terrorism Debate in West Germany., 2005 (Box 3)
  - Winkes, Gus, The Path of the Righteous: Conservative Social Policy in the United States and the Origins of Faith-Based Initiatives., May 20, 2005 (Box 3)
  - Young, Daniel, "Stories from a Dying Planet:" Greenpeace, Earth First!, Earth Liberation Front and the Narratives of Radical Environmentalism., May 20, 2005 (Box 3)
- Theses, 1965-1990; Accession ARCH-2005-255
  - Bonini, Cissie R., A Study of Richard Morison and evidences of Protestantism in his three propaganda books for Henry VIII., 1969 (Box 1)
  - Christensen, C. Diane, Sixteenth and seventeenth century Puritan attitudes toward the child and the family., 1965 (Box 1)
  - Haertl, Gregory, The Percys, the Nevilles, the North, and England, 1399-1461., 1981 (Box 1)
  - Hashimoto, Beverly, The decline of hospitality in Tudor England., 1974 (Box 1)
  - Hebenton, Barbara, Spanish ambassadors and Elizabethan foreign policy 1558-72., 1985 (Box 1)
  - Horton, Jonathan, Thomas Bradwardine and the origins of modern mechanics., 1976 (Box 1)
  - LeVan, Mary Lou, On the authenticity of a runic artifact., 1984 (Box 2)
  - Pursell, Brennan, On the historiography of Henry VII; the propagation of the early Tudor myth., 1990 (Box 2)
  - Slusser, Susan, Berkenhead and Nedham: fathers of modern journalism., 1988 (Box 2)
  - Wanlass, Jeanne, Touch not mine anointed: The reaction of the French to the execution of Charles I of England in their conception of monarchy., 1990 (Box 2)
- Theses, 2006; Accession ARCH-2006-221
  - Atura, Kim Estelle Bendersky, Ideology of independence: the Chilean Supreme Court and the Allende Presidency., May 2006 (Box 1)
  - Babilian, Silvia Araxie, The legacy of a founder: James Madison at Montpelier, 1817-1836., May 2006 (Box 1)
  - Brege, Brian, Artillery, fortification, and war: Renaissance Ferrara under Alfonso I d'Este 1505-1534., May 2006 (Box 1)
  - Cahill, Carolyn, Rediscovering Stockton history: examing the formative years., May 2006 (Box 1)
  - Ferrand-Andrew, Colleen, Shaping history, shaping culture: the evolution of the American pageant., 2006 (Box 1)
  - Fetter-Vorm, Jonathan, Curious Memories and Tragic Cases., 2006 (Box 1)
  - Graham, Jennifer Ann, Powering influence: American use of energy as a diplomatic tool in relations with Egypt, 1974-1979., June 2006 (Box 1)
  - Hira, Elizabeth, Arriving at the independence struggle: the genesis of colonialism in British Guiana., May 2006 (Box 1)
  - Jackson, Kirsten, Political power and the Black economy: a case study of the voting rights movement in Tuskegee, Alabama., May 2006 (Box 2)
  - Kurz, Nathaniel, Writing and rewriting the Balfour Declaration: the Manchester Zionists and Chaim Weizmann., 2006 (Box 2)
  - Lence, Bryan, Mormons and Polynesians: missionary zeal and racial exclusion., May 2006 (Box 2)
  - McFarland, Victor, A city institution: Whig ideology and the founding of the Boston Public Library., 2006 (Box 2)
  - Mill, N. Elizabeth, Sick building syndrome and other public health deceits: how the tobacco industry subverted science on air quality to save indoor smoking the the 1980s., May 2006 (Box 2)
  - Navarro, Paul, Maoism in the Andes: a concise history of the Partido Communista del Peru-Patria Roja (1960-1992)., May 2006 (Box 2)
  - Rapp-Hooper, Mira, A movement betrayed: the rank-and-file experience in the CPUSA and the 1956 Communist Party crisis., May 2006 (Box 2)
  - Stevenson, Terrell, From Mongoloid idiocy to Down Syndrome: the weight of language on people with Trisomy 21 from 1866 to the present., May 2006 (Box 2)
- Theses, 2007; Accession ARCH-2007-149
  - Abbey, Tristan, A Proud Tradition: Operation Ajax and Covert Action in the Early Cold War., May 2007 (Box 1)
  - Durning, R. Peter, Operation "Lentil": The Decision Behind the Ethnic Cleansing of Chechnya-Ingushetia In the Late Stages of the Second World War., May 2007 (Box 1)
  - Janik, Adam Christopher, Polish National Identity and the Upper Silesian Plebiscite., May 2007 (Box 1)
  - Loveridge, Jack, Strike the Sleeping Bharat: The 1918-1919 Influenza Pandemic in the Punjab., May 2007 (Box 1)
  - McGarr, Kathryn Jane, Reel Men: Changing Conceptions of Masculinity in the Films of William Wyler, 1945 to 1960., May 2007 (Box 1)
  - Shreve, Katherine, Propaganda, Polemic, and Powder: Portrayals of the Gunpowder Plot in 17th Century England., May 2007 (Box 1)
  - Sohns, Olivia, Quasim Amin: First Arab Feminist? (Intersection of Nation, Class, and Gender in Turn-of-the-Century Egypt)., May 2007 (Box 1)
  - Weiner, Josh F., Reconsidering the United States-Israel Relationship, 1970-1973: Oil, Phantoms and the Soviet Union., May 2007 (Box 1)
  - Wood, Andrew A., The British Labour Party and the Russian Revolutions, 1915-1918., May 2007 (Box 1)
  - Yokoyama, Reid Yoshio, Return, Rebuild and Redevelop: Japanese American Resettlement in San Francisco, 1945-1958., May 2007 (Box 1)
  - Zallen, Jeremy B., Boston's Forgotten Epidemic: Untold Stories of the 1918 Influenza and How We Have Begun to Remember., May 2007 (Box 1)
- Theses, Accession ARCH-2011-152
  - Abernethy, Jonathan Sloan, Politics in the streets: the Watts Rebellion of 1965., 1991 (Box 1)
  - Arriola, Christopher, Silent segregation: the history of Mexican American school segregation in El Modena, California., 1992 (Box 1)
  - Eckert, Cynthia, Setting limits: enforcement of prostitution laws, Oakland, California, 1934-1954., 1989 (Box 1)
  - Feinberg, Melissa, The experiences of women in Occupied Poland, 1939-1945., 1992 (Box 1)
  - Glaser, Gabrielle C., Culture and power: the Haitian intellectual response to the United States Marine occupation, 1915-1934., 1986 (Box 1)
  - Kasierski, Stephen G., Giving out the Psalm: the English roots of Samuel Slater's American success., 1988 (Box 1)
  - Lynch, Christopher K., The politician as historian: Winston Spencer Churchill and the Dardanelles., 1986 (Box 1)
  - Wander, Susan, A patrician woman in Quattrocento Florence: the letters of Alessandra Macinghi Negli Strozzi., 1987 (Box 1)
  - Wan, Christine D., Redefining the patriarch's wife: an exploration of the compatibility of patriarchal political theory with seventeenth-century proto-feminism., 1996 (Box 1)
  - Velazquez, Jorge, Bruce Barton: a progressive in the midst of change., 1989 (Box 1)
  - Sheidley, Nathaniel J., Between emancipation and panic: freedpeople, farmers and the colonial state at the Cape of Good Hope, 1838-1851., 1990 (Box 1)
  - Doon, Tiffany A., Race and labor in California in the late 19th Century: a case study of the New Almaden Quicksilver Mine., 1988 (Box 2)
  - Sellers, John H., Idealism, alliance, and empire: U.S. foreign policy toward British colonialism in Southeast Asia 1941-1945., 1988 (Box 2)
  - Wilcox, Andrew, The remaking of Zion: hydraulic development in Israel, 1948-1967., 1992 (Box 2)
  - Copass, Cloantha, Cllimbing for her rights: Annie Smith Peck, 1850-1935., 1989 (Box 2)
  - Stern, Nicole Gaye, Chiricahua Apache prisoners of war: the twenty-eight year ordeal of a proud people., 1992 (Box 2)
  - Mar, Lisa Rose, The Mar-Sue family's quest for survival in British columbia, 1914-1949., 1992 (Box 2)
  - Mackenzie, Emily K., "[N]othing has made up for a single day of suffering:" the women of Ravensbrück, 1939-45., 1992 (Box 2)
  - Shah, Manish S., The use of film on the American home front: the Why We Fight series and the films of Preston Sturges., 1994 (Box 2)
  - Sun, Tammy Wei-Ling, "Not only a women's cause": men in the British suffrage movement, 1907-1914., 1993 (Box 2)
  - Clark, Lisa, The effects of the transfer of Louisiana territory from Franco-Iberian domination to American rule on the free people of color in New Orleans, 1763-1830., 1995 (Box 2)
  - Nguyen, Marie Huong, Defining the sister-god: Ptolemaic politics, society and agenda in the dichotomous images of Arsinoë II Philadelphos., 2001 (Box 2)
  - Markou, Ouriana, Unorthodox statesman., 1992 (Box 3)
  - Crnja, Zoran, Recent experience with currency convertibility in Eastern Europe., 1993 (Box 3)
- Theses, 2008-2011; Accession ARCH-2012-004
  - Jacobs, Rebecca A., Living history: Soviet Jewish immigrants in the San Francisco Bay Area, 1967-present., 2008 (Box 1)
  - Kilner, Kathryn Rigaud, History and national identity in Chile's national art museum., 2008 (Box 1)
  - Klurfeld, Zachary, From no-party man to partisan politician: the late career of Elbridge Gerry., 2008 (Box 1)
  - Mannapperuma, Menesha, From separaism to coalition building: the politics of the women;s building in San Francisco, California, 1970-1991., 2008 (Box 1)
  - Meyerson, Andy, From savage to celebrity: how Lili'uokalani's music shaped the American perception of her character and the Kanaka Maoli from 1893 to 1898., 2008 (Box 1)
  - Pugliese, Carla, There is only one other: how precedent and politics homogenized state representations of the overseas France, 1945-1960., 2008 (Box 1)
  - Qiu, Wangshu, An unresolved legacy: the evolution of popular Chinese memories of the Korean War., 2008 (Box 1)
  - Smith, Alexis Lauren, Powdering their noses: the taboo subculture of female snuff usage in antebellum America., 2008 (Box 1)
  - Beck, Stephanie, Roll up your sleeves for President Ford: the national influenza immunization program of 1976., 2009 (Box 1)
  - Bellows-Blakely, Sarah, Colonial change and contested responses: inter-ethnic conflict during Kenya's Mau Mau War of 1952-1960., 2009 (Box 1)
  - Craft, Paul, Old guard, new age, Robert A. Taft, Barry M. Goldwater, and American foreign policy, 1950-1953., 2009 (Box 2)
  - Egan, Sophie, Lasting loss: the long-term impact of World War II restrictions on Bay Area Italian-American families., 2009 (Box 2)
  - Eppler, Benjamin, Wider still, and wider: expanding the British empire in interwar Bahrain., 2009 (Box 2)
  - Hironaka, Christine, Violence and murder in the Tule Lake Segregation Center: three case studies of community factionalism and administrative misrule, October 1943-July 1944., 2009 (Box 2)
  - Hohnmann, James P., Into the jaws of defeat: how Ronald Reagan lost the 1976 election and remade the national political order., 2009 (Box 2)
  - Horowitz, Jake, The Rogers Plan of 1969: the making and shaping of U.S. foreign policy in the Arab-Israeli conflict., 2009 (Box 2)
  - Lehman, Travis, A lost chapter in New Zealand history: the failure of the Parkhurst Prison experiment and the experience of the Parkhurst boys in New Zealand., 2009 (Box 2)
  - Leinsdorf, Otto Manfred, Between the book and the lamp: subjectivity and hermenutics in the work of Michel Foucault., 2009 (Box 2)
  - Lomeli, Andrew M., The perfect workers: agribusiness' abuse of the bracero program in the American southwest, 1942-1964., 2009 (Box 3)
  - Merz, Alexa, Complicated medicine: tuberculosis and the pursuit of health in California, 1840-1899., 2009 (Box 3)
  - Schneider, Andrew, When silence is betrayal: American colonialism and Martin Luther King Jr.'s opposition to the Vietnam War., 2009 (Box 3)
  - Simpson, Michael, The agonizing Wilsonian: David Lawrence, public opinion, and foreign policy, 1937-1954., 2009 (Box 3)
  - Golabek-Goldman, Sarah, Polish historical memory of the Holocaust., 2010 (Box 3)
  - Kabaker, Yishai, Shifting sands: military lessons of the first Gulf War., 2010 (Box 3)
  - Knight, Jessica, Mutual defense: Washington, Congress, and the civil-military relationship, 1775-1783., 2010 (Box 3)
  - Lawson, Kirsty, Behind closed doors: the public role of alchemical secrets in the Ashmolean Museum., 2010 (Box 3)
  - Magun, Kyla, A missed opportunity for a national health program? An analysis of the limited effect of the national health conference of July 18-20, 1938., 2010 (Box 4)
  - Oehmke, Joseph, "The greatest piece of diplomacy ever": the story of the 1949 San Francisco Seals goodwill tour of Japan., 2010 (Box 4)
  - Schickler, Carmi, A life of contrasts: Vernon Lyman Kellogg and World War I., 2010 (Box 4)
  - Schnayder, Evgenia, Gone with the wind: Texas, California, and the changing interpretations of the Amiercan Civil War in modern United States history textbooks., 2010 (Box 4)
  - Skelton, Christopher, Medicine, education, empire: Sir James Cantlie and the Hong Kong College of Medicine for Chinese, 1887-1912., 2010 (Box 4)
  - Cho, Christie Sung-Ah, The case for Korea: Korean American participation in the independence movement, 1910-1919., 2010 (Box 4)
  - Zegura, Krista, The TVA and the people: a case study of Norris Dam., 2010 (Box 5)
  - Albada, Michael, Drawn to expectations: competing portrayals of Johann Gottlieb Fichte in the Weimar Republic, 1918-1933., 2011 (Box 4)
  - Basu, Jacqueline, John Adams: the transatlantic republican: debating against philosophe political institutions, social theory, and theoretical method., 2011 (Box 4)
  - De Groot, Michael B., Alternate visions: the tangled lives and politics of Hans Bethe and Edward Teller., 2011 (Box 4)
  - Hadidi, Mona, My Islam: an exploration of the development of Muslim American identities, 1965-present., 2011 (Box 4)
  - Karlin-Neumann, Zev M., Lobbying for Greatness: the Special Committee on the Senate Reception Room and the rise of John F. Kennedy., 2011 (Box 5)
  - Koch, Travis A., Sowing seeds of progress: Liberty Hyde Bailey and the country life phase of the American conservation movement., 2011 (Box 5)
  - Sy, Andrea Denise Chua, Forging a new identity under fire: the development of Chinese-Filipino consciousness through international pressure and the heat of World War II., 2011 (Box 5)
  - Warma, Zachary Russell, "What happens when Sigma Chi pledges a Negro": the Alpha Omega chapter, Stanford University, and the national struggle over fraternal discrimination., 2011 (Box 5)
  - Ziv, Stav, Dancing through cracks in the Iron Curtain: U.S.-Soviet ballet tours in Cold War cultural exchange, 1958-1962., 2011 (Box 5)
  - Osei-Opare, Kwadwo Nana, The continued fight against neo-colonialism: a case study of Dr. Kwame Nkrumah and Patrice Lumumba., 2011 (Box 5)
  - Osei-Opare, Kwadwo Nana, The continued fight against neo-colonialism: a case study of Dr. Kwame Nkrumah and Patrice Lumumba. Supporting material and copies of material from the George Padmore Library (Accra, Ghana) on Ghana -- Africa relations in the 1960s. (Box 6)
- Theses, Accession ARCH-2012-049
  - Flocks, Sally, Ideology without revolution: feminists' attitudes towards motherhood and child-rearing 1888-1920., 1973 (Box 1)
  - Klein, Patrick F., Cold War liberalism: American liberal social thought in the 1950's., 1970 (Box 1)
  - Payne, Marshall, Anglo-American cooperation in atomic energy research 1943-1947., 1979 (Box 1)
  - Cushing, Mark L., The American liberal Catholic tradition, 1880-1965: a study of the ideas of John Ireland, John Ryan, and John Courtney Murray., 1975 (Box 1)
  - Silverman, Scott, Chester Rowell and reform in Fresno, California: 1898-1905., 1971 (Box 1)
  - Ayer, Donald B., An interpretative essay on millennialism and its effect on the developing American character., 1971 (Box 1)
  - Walt, Christopher, American business and European recovery, 1944-1951., 1972 (Box 1)
  - Moe, Stephen A., The nation triumphant: the historical writings of Henry Adams, Theodore Roosevelt, and Woodrow Wilson., 1970 (Box 1)
  - Rosene, Deborah K., Power and impotence: an hypothesis; male responses to the emancipation of woman, 1880-1920., 1971 (Box 1)
  - Killefer, Gail, Moral responsibility: Ralph Waldo Emerson and William James., 1975 (Box 1)
- Theses, 2012-2014; Accession ARCH-20114-132
  - Aguilar, Andrew Scott, Un mal necessaire: Secular Interventions in French Islam, 1980-2013, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Anderson, Hilary, Consensus vs. Concession: Labour Party Nuclear Weapons Policy Decision-Making, 1941-1980, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Antonsen, Rachel, Resisting Eviction on Cairo's Nile Islands, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Barrios, Maria, Lavoisier's Chemistry at Work: The Revolutionary Renovation of French Gunpowder Production, 1775-1813, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Belitz, Hannah, Can We Move Forward Without Looking Back? The Bush Administration's Policy of "Enchanted Interrogation" Techniques and the Obama Administration's Decision to Avoid Retrospection, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Boyar, Keegan F.P., Fanatics or Freedom Fighters? An Analysis of Depictions of the Tomochic Rebellion in the Mexico City Press, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bretthauer, Kevin, The Lion and the Samurai: Reinterpreting the Anglo-Japanese Alliance., 2012 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Coggeshall, Samuel, The Created Word and the Word-Creator: Transrationality and Soviet Language Policy, 1913-1925, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Danford, Ellen, "More Poisonous than any He-Serpent:" Lodowick Muggleton's Aversion to Female Prophecy, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Dang, Bianca, The Fate of the "Negro Republic": The Santo Domingo Affair as a Lens for African American Visions of Reconstruction, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Fair, Elizabeth, The Ellusive Lillian Hellman and Her Scoundrel Time: Her Politics, Her Self-Representation, and the Controversy, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Geiser, Kelsey, Mothers in the Italian Interwar Years: Feminism, Fascism and the Changing Society Role of Italian Women, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Gonzalez, Karla, Remember September 11: Chilean Memory of the U.S. Role in Chile's Coup d'etat, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Groenendaal, Laura, Islands of Capital: The Qualifying Industrial Zones in Jordan, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Guadarrama, Alexis, Old Inquisition, New Land: Examining Claims of Religious Toleration between Old and New Christians in Early Colonial Brazil, 1591-1595, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Hughes, Michael, The New Deal Jurisprudence of Chief Justice Charles Evans Hughes and Justice Owen Roberts: Approaches in Transition, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Khan, Sahar, The Crisis of Post-Colonial Secularism in India Something Exceptional- Typical: Violence in Jabalpur, 1961, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Lassere, John, Lineage and Nation: Pan-Dialect Chinese Ethnogenesis in Singapore, 1900-1942, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Lattanzi, Maria, They Died So We Could Live: Commemoration and Memorialization of a Palestinian National Past, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Link, Josephine, Breaking the Glass Closet: Origins of the Gay Community at Stanford, 1971-1985, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Monroe, Caitlin, Land, Violence, History: Examining the Relationship between Claims to Territory, State Weakness, and Historical Memory in Local Conflict in Eastern Democratic Republic of Congo, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Moore, Jessica, Rape, Race, and Reporting: Press Coverage of Sexual Violence in Black and White American Newspapers, 1920-1945, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Moses, Ann Tyler, The Paper Dead: The American Civil War, as Told and Tempered by Its Photographs, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Nelson, David S., Critical Hope: An Intellectual History of Irving Howe, 1920-1954, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Novak, Layne, Knowing and Being: The Imagination in British Empiricism, 1650- 1750, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Peterson, Aaron, Terrible Lizards and the Wrath of God: The Religious Gothic in Representations of Dinosaurs and the Ancient World, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Prossnitz, Annie, In My Hand, A Song Remains: Examining the Nazi Concentration Camp Universe Through the Lens of Music, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Schreier, Jeremy Rafael, How Can We Sing the Song of the Lord in a Foreign Land? Jewish Music and Identity in the Life and Work of Salamone Rossi (ca. 1570-1630), 2014 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Steinbach, John, The Long Shadow of Nuremburg: The Evolving Wartime Jurisprudence of Justice Robert H. Jackson, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Tran, Van Anh, Hawks, Doves, and the Refugee Flight: Implications of Historical Memory and Learning About the Viet Nam War among the Second Generation, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Unterreiner, Miles, Race, Memory, and Law in the Tacoma Chinese Expulsion of 1885, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Urquiza, Maritza, A Woman of the Ages: Conceptualizing an Exhibit about the Life and Times of Juana Briones, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Vanderboll, Kathryn, Daughters of Liberty and Industry: Colonial American Women and Textile Boycotts in the Eighteenth Century Newspaper, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Warner, Anne, From Freedom to Forgiveness: How Time and Politics Shaped the Afterlife Narrative of the Amy Biehl Story, 2012 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Wieland, Mark, Althing Considered: Thwarting Corruption and Greed at Medieval Iceland's National Assembly, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 35)